Laser light usually a spatially coherent,
narrow low-divergence beam, that can be manipulated
with lenses.
In this experiment our aim is to find the
laser beam divergence and spotsize using a
detector.
The light emitted by a laser is confined to
a rather narrow cone; but, as the beam propagates
outward, it slowly diverges or fans out.
At the output aperture of the laser, the beam
diameter is d.
Its beam divergence angle , usually expressed
in milliradians.
In traversing a distance , the beam diverges
to a circle of diameter .
i.e, The beam divergence is an angular measure
of increase in beam diameter with distance
from the optical aperture from which the electromagnetic
beam emerges.
The spot size of the beam is the radial distance
-- from the center of maximum irradiance
or intensity to the 1/e2 points.
Procedure
set a laser and a detector(for measuring the
intensity) on an optical breadboard.
Align the laser beam -- in such a way that
laser beam can fall on detector.
Fix a distance for the detector -- and take
intensity measurements of the beam along a
horizontal line -- passing the point with
the maximum intensity.
Repeat the previous step for different variants.
Calculate the beam divergence by calculating
the maximum intensity of the beam,
which helps in calculating the beam spot size,
at different distances from the laser with
the help of the optical bread board.
Now, we can observe that the divergence of
a laser beam is proportional to its wavelength
-- and inversely proportional to the diameter
of the beam -- at its narrowest point.